Council for Responsible Genetics Records MS229
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Council for Responsible Genetics Records
1983 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Council for Responsible Genetics
MS229
13.2 Linear Feet 11 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject, as received from the Council for Responsible Genetics.
Custodial History
The Council for Responsible Genetics donated this collection to Digital Collections and Archives in October 2015. Sheldon Krimsky, professor of Urban and Environmental and Policy and Adjunct Professor in Public Health and Family Medicine at Tufts University, serves as the Council for Responsible Genetics Chair of the Board. Professor Krimsky coordinated the donation of this collection to DCA.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the administration and work of the Council for Responsible Genetics dating back to its founding in 1983. Administrative records include Board of Directors bylaws, meeting minutes, budgets, fundraising and grant records, and annual reports. The bulk of the collection consists of files documenting the Council's many programs related to the social, ethical and environmental implications of genetic technologies, including research, position papers, and advocacy. Programs documented include the Safe Seed Project; issues related to human genetics, testing, privacy, and discrimination; genetic engineering and cloning; and more.
Biographical / Historical
The Council for Responsible Genetics (CRG) is a nonprofit, non-government organization founded in Cambridge, Massachusetts in 1983. The organization was founded by a group of scientists and advocates to publicly address concerns over the social and civic implications of developments in biotechnology and applied genetics, a topic that had previously received little public attention.
Early activities included a briefing for the United States Congress in 1985 and a panel for the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 1986, both on the topic of gene splicing for biological weapons. CRG began publishing GeneWatch, a magazine addressing the implications of scientific developments in applied genetics, in 1983.
CRG created the Safe Seed Campaign in 1999 to increase the transparency of genetic modification in commercially sold seeds, in order to help consumers make informed purchases. By 2001 ten percent of seed catalogs in the United States used the "Safe Seed Pledge," ensuring that the seeds being sold were not genetically modified. CRG later worked to found and direct the Coalition for Genetic Fairness, which comprised over 500 separate organizations in support of the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act (GINA). GINA was signed into law in 2008, protecting Americans from discrimination by employers and health insurers based on genetic information. Additionally, in support of GINA, CRG compiled the first documentation concerning individuals who had been discriminated against by employers and insurance agencies based on family genetic history.
Sheldon Krimsky, professor of Urban and Environmental and Policy and Adjunct Professor in Public Health and Family Medicine at Tufts University, serves as the Council for Responsible Genetics Chair of the Board.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Council for Responsible Genetics; Bioethics; Genetics--Social aspects; Faculty research
- Administrative and program files, 1983 -- 2014; MS229.001; 13.2 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  Administrative records include Board of Directors bylaws, meeting minutes, budgets, fundraising and grant records, and annual reports. Program files document the Council's work related to the social, ethical and environmental implications of genetic technologies, including research, position papers, and advocacy. Programs documented include the Safe Seed Project; issues related to human genetics, testing, privacy, and discrimination; genetic engineering and cloning; and more.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by subject.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Program activities and meeting minutes, 1983 -- 1997; MS229.001.001 (Box 1)
    Programs documented include human genetics, testing, and discrimination including newborn screening and eugenics; informed consent in genetic research; cancer and genetic testing; insurance companies and genetic testing; biotechnology and women's health; and biological labs. Also included are Board of Directors meeting minutes, budgets, grant records, and annual reports.
  - Program activities and meeting minutes, 1998 -- 2004; MS229.001.002 (Box 2)
    Programs documented include human genetics, testing, and discrimination including newborn screening; embryo and human cloning; gene therapy; patents on life; and the Boston University biological labs controversy. Also included are Board of Directors meeting minutes, bylaws, budgets, and annual reports.
  - Program activities and meeting minutes, 2005 -- 2014; MS229.001.003 (Box 3)
    Programs documented include Safe Seed Project; embryo research; human growth hormone; human genetics, testing, and discrimination; race and genetics and race and forensic DNA databanks; and biological labs and biological weapons. Also included are Board of Directors meeting minutes, budgets, annual reports, and strategic planning documents; articles written by CRG members, and website documentation.
  - Safe Seed and No Patents on Life programs, 1990 -- 2010; MS229.001.004 (Box 4)
  - Genetically modified organisms and related issues, 1990 -- 2010; MS229.001.005 (Box 5)
    Includes files on genetically engineered food and food labeling (GMO, non-GMO, and organic); Monsanto; genetic pollution in agriculture; biotechnology and the environment; L-tryptophan; Bovine Growth Hormone; and biodiversity.
  - DNA and forensic DNA databanks, 1990 -- 2010; MS229.001.006 (Box 6)
    Includes files on DNA databanks in individual states; forensic DNA databanks and race; and a legal challenge to the Department of Defense's DNA databank program, Mayfield, et al. v. John H.Dalton, Secretary of the Navy, et al.
  - Genetic screening and testing; Genetic privacy and discrimination, 1990 -- 2010; MS229.001.007 (Box 7)
  - Genetic discrimination: Federal and state laws and cases, 1990 -- 2010; MS229.001.008 (Box 8)
    Documentation of discriminatory federal and state legislation (bills and laws), including files on individual state laws. Also included are copies of records of a legal challenge to the Department of Defense's DNA databank program, Mayfield, et al. v. John H.Dalton, Secretary of the Navy, et al.
  - Women & biotech, surrogacy, prenatal genetic screening, cloning, and Americans with Disabilities Act, 1990 -- 2010; MS229.001.009 (Box 9)
    Includes files on the Human Genome Project, stem cell research, human cloning, gene therapy, and germline manipulation.
  - Foundation gift and grant files, 1989 -- 2012; MS229.001.010 (Box 10)
  - Position papers, 1986-2002; Financial records, 1999-2011, MS229.001.011 (Box 11)
    Position papers include statements on genetic engineering; genetically engineered foods; patents on genes and organisms; genetic testing, privacy, and discrimination; human cloning; and biotechnology and biological weapons. Financial records include year-end financial statements and audit reports and foundation grants applied for.